<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discouerie of the countries of Tartaria, Scithia, &amp; Cataya, by the northeast: with the maners, fashions, and orders which are vsed in those countries. / Set foorth by Iohn Frampton merchaunt.</title>
            <author>Frampton, John, fl. 1577-1596.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S92572</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52633240</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52633240</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174043</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174043)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2115:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discouerie of the countries of Tartaria, Scithia, &amp; Cataya, by the northeast: with the maners, fashions, and orders which are vsed in those countries. / Set foorth by Iohn Frampton merchaunt.</title>
                  <author>Frampton, John, fl. 1577-1596.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 40 [i.e. 80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Thomas Dawson.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Jmprinted at London at the three Cranes in the Vintree, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1580.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within border of printers' ornaments; initials.</note>
                  <note>Pages numbered on recto only.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.]⁴, A-E⁸.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: last leaf torn, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Asia --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Africa, East --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174043:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Diſcouerie of the</hi> countries of Tartaria, Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia, &amp; Cataya, by the North-Eaſt: With the maners, <hi>faſhions, and orders which are vſed in thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Set foorth by Iohn Frampton mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> at the three Cranes <hi>in the Vintree, by Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> Dawſon. 1580.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:174043:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174043:2"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>To the right worſhipfull</hi> ſyr Rowland Hayward knight, and to maſter George Barne, Aldermen of <hi>the citie of London, and gouernours of the</hi> worſhipfull company of the merchaunts ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturers for diſcouerie of newe trades, and to the aſsiſtents &amp; generalitie of all the ſayd worſhipfull fellowſhip, Iohn Frampton wiſheth all happye ſucceſſe in all their attempts.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here came of late to my hands, (right vvor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipfull) a diſcours of the ſeueral &amp; ſundrye cuſtomes, and manners of diuers nations, which are founde to inhabite in the North, in the North Eaſt, and in
<pb facs="tcp:174043:3"/> the Eaſt partes of the worlde, &amp;c. Collected and written by a certaine learned man called Franciſco Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mara, a reader in Spayne, in the citie of Cadiz, and dedicated by him to the moſte excellent Lorde, Don Iohn Claros de Guzman Earle of Niebla, and inheriter of the duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and eſtate of Medina Cido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia: And vnderſtanding the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of your worthie enterpriſe, for the diſcouerie of the paſſages by ſea to all thoſe regions of the North, and Northeaſt, &amp;c. for very great zeale I beare to you, and of deſire I had to farther you in ſo famous an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, I tooke the tranſlation of the ſame worke in hande, and beſtowed the ſame in writing on ſuch as you ſent in the ſayde diſcouerie in your two Pineſſes, late ſent forth, that fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on thoſe coaſtes, foreknowing the natures of thoſe people, they
<pb facs="tcp:174043:3"/> might the better ſhunne perilles, and on the other ſide take the benefite of the place the better. And nowe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thought good to committ the ſame to print, and to dedicate the ſame to your worſhips, that eache of you may be partaker of the contents, praying you to accept of my ſmall trauell, &amp; good meaning, and to take the ſame in good parte, wiſhing that I were more able to do you pleaſure or ſeruice, to the furtherance of ſo noble an enterpriſe: ſince the ſame tendeth to the ample vent of our cloth, and other our commodities of England, to the increaſe of our nauie, to the ſupply of ſundry our wants, and to the annoy of the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall enemies of this kingdome, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you ſhal pleaſe God, purchace the prayer of the poore, and not offende any one or other honeſt perſon of the realme, and ſo I commit your
<pb facs="tcp:174043:4"/> worſhips to God, wiſhing the moſte happy ſucceſſe that is to be wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From London <date>this xv. of Iuly. 1580.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your worſhips to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, <hi>Iohn Frampton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:174043:4"/>
            <head>¶ Of the Region of <hi>Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> and of the Lawes and power of the <hi>Tartars.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Artaria,</hi> which by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name is called <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall,</hi> as <hi>Vicencio</hi> writeth, ſtandeth towardes the northeaſt, and at the Eaſt parte ioyneth with the Land of the <hi>Catheos</hi> and <hi>Solangos:</hi> on the South parte it bordereth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Country of <hi>Sartanecos,</hi> &amp; on the Weſt parte with that of the <hi>Naymanos,</hi> and of the North parte it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed about with the Occean Seas. It was called <hi>Tartaria,</hi> by reaſon of a Riuer running by it, called <hi>Tartar,</hi> and is a Region where the greateſt parte is full of Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and the moſt part of the plaine fields verie ſandie, being a barren countrey, ſauing that ſome parte of it is ouerflowen with the waters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ryuers, &amp; a great parte thereof is wilderneſſe &amp; litle inhabited. Ther are no Cities nor Townes in it, ſauing onelye the Citie of <hi>Cracuris.</hi> Ther is ſo great want and ſmal ſtore of wood in it, that the people there are driuen to vſe for the moſt parte the offall and dung of Oxen and Horſes for their fuel, aſwell in roſting and boyling their victuals,
<pb facs="tcp:174043:5"/> as otherwiſe. The ayre of this Region is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry intemperate, and full of ſtormes and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, that in the ſommer time there are ſuch wonderfull thunders and lightninges, that men die for very feare of the ſame. At other times there is great heat, and immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followeth verye extreame colde, and ſnowe falling very thicke. The windes there are ſo boyſterous an ſtrong almoſt continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, that they drawe men backward as they are ryding on their iournyes, ouerthrowing them to the ground, and alſo blowe vp trees by the rootes, and to conclude do much other harme. In the winter it neuer rayneth, in the ſummer many times, and at euery of the ſame ſo little, that ſcarſelye it wetteth the ground: and yet for all this it is a rich coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of all kinde of cattell, as well oxen as Camels, &amp;c. Of beaſtes of ſeruice and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes there is ſo great ſtore and plentie, that it is to be ſuppoſed, there are not ſo many moe in all the reſt of the worlde. There were at the beginning in this Realme foure ſortes of people: The firſt ſorte called <hi>Yeca Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales,</hi> which is as much to ſaye the great <hi>Mongales:</hi> The ſecond ſorte called <hi>Sumon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales,</hi> which ſignifieth the <hi>Mongales</hi> of the water, becauſe they dwell neere to the Riuer
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:174043:5"/> 
               <hi>Tartar,</hi> whereof they beare the name of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars:</hi> The third are called <hi>Mercat,</hi> and the fourth ſorte <hi>Metrit:</hi> All theſe had one man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſhape of body, and vſed all one lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. Their manner of lyuing at the firſte was fearce &amp; barbarous, without any lawes or policie, they lyued by the increaſe of rattell, and were a bruite people, and little regarded among the <hi>Scithians.</hi> Afterwarde in proceſſe of tyme they deuided and ſeuered them ſelues into certaine places and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to take theyr Captaines in companie which had charge of the whole common wealth, and yet for all that ceaſed not to pay tribute to the <hi>Naymanos,</hi> which next adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to them, vntill that by chaunce one <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſta</hi> a man brought vp among them, was elected for their king, by meanes of an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle and reuelation. This man immediately after he had receiued the Empire and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne gouernment, commaunded that all honour accuſtomed to be done to the deuill, ſhould ceaſſe, and eſtabliſhed by his generall edicte, that all people ſhoulde honour and worſhip one onelye GOD, the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt, greateſt and beſt of all others, and alſo gaue expreſſe commandement, that it ſhould be generally publiſhed that he had receyued the Realme by the ſame Gods prouidence.
<pb facs="tcp:174043:6"/> After this he commaunded that all ſuch as could beare armour, ſhould come forthwith and repreſent them ſelues before him by a certeine day. And all the people apt for the warres being come together, he in his owne perſon hauing taken the number of them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided them in order, and appoynted ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Corporals, Sargents, Captaines and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronels. &amp;c. After this, to proue what force and power he had in the empire and ſupreme authoritie: he commaunded ſeuen of the moſt principall men that firſt had the charge and gouernment of all the Realme, to kill their ſonnes with their owne handes, the which though it was and ſeemed a very hard thing vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet they acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed it forthwith, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing moued thervnto, partly for feare of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, and partly by reaſon of a deuout ſuperſtition in that they had conceiued a ſtedfaſt beliefe that God was the beginning and foundation of that kingdome, and that if they refuſed to obey the commaundementes of their king, they committed not an offence to him, but to God. And with this truſt and power ſo rayſed, the king <hi>Canguiſta,</hi> firſt of all brought vnder his ſubiection, by force of armes, the <hi>Scithians</hi> that bordered vpon his countrey making them his tributaries, with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:174043:6"/> the other people alſo to whom his owne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects had before payed tribute, and forthwith ſet vpon diuers other nations both farre and neere from his owne dominions, hauing ſo proſperous ſucceſſe, that he brought in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection vnder his Empyre all the Realmes, Dominions &amp; nations, euen from <hi>Scithia</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Mediterran</hi> ſea, wher the Sun ryſeth, &amp; ſome what more, inſomuch that with reaſon he intituleth him ſelfe Lord and Emperour of all the Eaſt partes.</p>
            <p>All the <hi>Tartars</hi> are of an euill ſhape in their bodies, the moſt part of them being of a ſmall ſtature. They haue great eyes, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding farre out, and the liddes thereof coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with very much hayre, in ſuch ſorte that there can but a litle of their eies be ſene, their faces are brode, they haue no beards, ſauing on their vpper lips, &amp; in the ſame haue but a few hayres, and thoſe very thin: al of them for the moſt part are ſlender in the waſt, in the fore pare of their heads they weare their hayre long like women of our countrey, and make two rowles thereof, and ſo gather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> behind their eares: and not only the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> do thus, but alſo ſuch as are ioyning nere to them do the like. They are light peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and good horſemen, but euill foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb facs="tcp:174043:7"/> none of them do go afoote, although they be very little. Their manner is to ride vpon horſes or oxen whether ſo euer they tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, and the women vſe Geldinges that are not fierce. They alſo vſe to haue their forheds decked with ſiluer and precious ſtones, and conceiue a great glorye, in that their horſes carry collers of belles to make a great iyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Their ſpeach is ſharpe and high, when they would ſinge they howle like wolues, when they drinke they ſhake the head, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they accuſtome to drinke ſo often, tyll they fall downe, and take it for great honour.</p>
            <p>They inhabite neither townes nor cities, but in the fieldes, as the <hi>Scithians</hi> did in the olde time, vnder Pauilions and Tentes: For the moſt parte are ſhepheardes. In the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they vſe to lyue in the plaine fieldes, in the Sommer they continue in the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, for the fruitefulneſſe of the paſture. They make their lodginges and plates of abode like a ſhoppe eyther of bowes, or of timber, couered with felt, and in the middeſt of theſe ſheddes, make a rounde windowe where the light commeth in, and the ſmoke goeth out, in the middeſt of the cottage is the fire, and their wiues and children alwayes about it. The men vſe to ſhoote in bowes,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174043:7"/> and to wraſtle, they are merueilous hunters, they ride a hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting armed on horſback, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſee any wilde beaſtes, they compaſſe them about, and euery one of them ſhooting his arow, they wound, &amp; take him. They haue no bread, vſe no table cloth nor napkins, and beleeue in one God onely, affyrming him to be the maker of all thinges, viſible and inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, they honour him not with any ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, but make certeine Iodls of felt, or ſilke, or the likeneſſe of a man, and put them on both ſides of their ſheddes or ſhoppes, praying them to keepe ſafe their cattell, and ſhewing great reuerence toward them, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them all the milke that they haue firſt of the cattell, and before they beginne to eate or drinke, they ſet their part before them. Any manner of beaſt that they kyll for to eate, they put his hart in a veſſell all night, and in the morning ſeeth and eate it. They honour and do ſacrifiſe likewiſe to the Sunne and Moone, to the foure Elements, and alſo the great <hi>Chaam</hi> their king and Lorde, whome they thinke to be the Sonne of God, and ſo honour him deuoutly, and do ſacrifice to him, and beleue that in al the world there is none better, nor of more dignitie then he, neyther wil they conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any other be named but be.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:174043:8"/>
            <p>This people in reſpect of them ſelues, thinking no other nation worthy to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with them, in wiſdome nor goodneſſe, and therfore will not willingly ſpeake with any other, but rather auoyd them ſelues from their companies. They call the Pope and al other Chriſtians dogges and Idolaters al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that they honour ſtones and ſtockes. They are much adicted to wicked arts, geue credit to dreames, and enterteine and allow ſuch as vſe the magicall ſcience and arte of diuination, and can enterpret their dreames: Alſo they aſke queſtions and receiue anſwer of their Idols, with ful perſwaſion and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe that God ſpeaketh in them. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what enterpriſe ſo euer they take in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, they begin and proceede in the ſame by the counſell of thoſe Idols. They behold and marke the weather very much, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Moone: for they make no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of one tyme more then of an other, nor honour any feſtiuall day, ne vſe any manner of faſting or abſtinence. At all times they liue after one faſhion, and are ſo coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, that what ſoeuer they ſee, if it like them well, if they cannot get it with the good will of the owner, being no <hi>Tartar,</hi> they take it from him by plaine ſtafford law, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174043:8"/> it a matter lawfull to be don by meanes of a commaundement and eſtabliſhment of the king their ſouereign Lord. For they haue an ordinance of their <hi>Canguiſta</hi> and <hi>Chaam</hi> their firſt king, that any manner of <hi>Tartar</hi> or <hi>Tartars</hi> ſeruaunt finding by the way as he trauaileth any horſe, man, or woman without a letter or ſafe conduct of the king, may ſenſe and take them as his owne, and enioy them foreuer. They lend their monye to ſuch as ſtand in neede of it, and take a certeine kind of vſurie, both very great and alſo intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: for they take after the rate often pounds vppon the hundred for euerie moneth, and if the vſurie money be not payde immediatly, then they they take further vſurie. They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine the people ſubued vnto them to paye ſo exceſſiue tribute and taxes, and ſo greatly moleſt and oppreſſe them, that there is no people read of, that ſo much moleſteth their tributarie ſubiects. Their couetouſneſſe is ſuch, as is ſkant credible to be beleeued, they are alwayes crauing and brybing, yea the moſt Lordes of all others, geue nothing to any, no not to ſuch as are in neceſſitie, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther giue to poore people almes: onelye in this they ſeeme worthy of ſome commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that if any gueſtes by chaunce come to
<pb facs="tcp:174043:9"/> them when they be at meate, and would take parte with them, they turne them not awaye nor diſturb them, but rather inuite them, and geue them of that they eate with much pitie. In their diet they are very filthy hauing nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tables to eate vppon, nor table clothes, nor napkins, &amp; vſe not to waſh their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds nor bodyes, nor clothes. They eate no bread, for they haue it not, nor any manner of hearbes, but feede onely with the fleſh of al manner of beaſtes, and likewiſe pigs fleſh, and of cats, horſes and rats: and when they take any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner of their enemies, to ſhew their crueltie the more, and the deſire they haue to reuenge them ſelues, ſomtimes they roaſt them at the fire, and after manye of them aſſemble and eate him, like vnto wolues, they teare him in peeces, and eate his fleſh, and take the blood the which they keepe in certein veſſelles and drink it, although that otherwiſe their accuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomed drinke is the mylke of beaſtes. They haue no wine among them, but if by chaunce any be brought thyther to them, they drinke it with great deſire and affection, as all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men do. Likewiſe they eate the lyce one of an other, taking them out of their heades, or any other place: and when they haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them, they ſay that they wil do ſo by theyr
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174043:9"/> enemies. They take it for a great euill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, when any part of their meate or drink falleth from them, or is loſt, and throw not their boanes to dogges, before they haue fully burniſhed them. They vſe ſuch ſcarcitie and niggardneſſe of all thinges, that they neyther kill nor eate any manner of beaſte while it is whole and ſounde, but when it is lame, or hath ſome impediment in the body, or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it beginneth to wax old, or by chaunce is ſicke: In all other thinges they are verye modeſt, for they content themſelues with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little meate. In the morning they drinke a veſſell full of mylke, and afterwarde manye tymes neyther eate nor drinke in al the day. The apparell they vſe is wel neere after one ſorte, as wel men as women. The men weare vpon their heades a certeine thing, not very depe, which is playn before, and behind hath a tayle well neere a ſpanne long, and as much in breadth, and bicauſe it may ſtande cloſe to the head, and not be blowne of for the winde, they haue certeine gardes ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it, neere to the eares, wherewith they binde them vnder the chinne. The mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried women weare a garment made lyke to a round baſket, a foote and a halfe long, and the hygher parte of them playne much
<pb facs="tcp:174043:10"/> after the faſhion of a boote, being of many coulours, al garniſhed and edged about with ſilke, or Peacocks feathers, and layde ouer with many precious ſtones, and golde: and the reſt of the bodye euery one apparelleth according to their habilities, the richeſt ſort of grayne and ſilke after the ſame manner that their huſbands do, they haue cotes made full of pleites, open in the left ſide, whereby they put them on and off, hauing four or fiue lowpes or buttons to keepe them together and faſt to theyr bodies. The apparell they weare in the ſommer, is for the moſt parte black, and that which they weare in the cold and rayny wether is white: theſe cloths reach no lower the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the knee: the mayde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are not eaſily knowne from the married wiues, nor the women from the men: for almoſt they haue the like faces and apparel that the men haue, euery one equally and after one ſort vſe all their ſmall apparell alike. When they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into battaile, ſome of them weare armour vpon their armes with certeine yron leaues, which they tye together with ſtringes, other vſe leather many times doubled, and in the like ſorte they arme their heades, there are few that vſe Launces, and long ſwordes, but commonly they carry ſhort ſwordes, three
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174043:10"/> ſpannes long, round with a ſharpe edge on the ſide, and with theſe they wounde their ſides when they fight. The horſmen are very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight, and great archers, and he is taken for more ſtrong and valiant that is more obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and laboreth moſt to preſerue the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre. They fight without wages, and are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſubtill and diligent in their battailes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all that they take in hand, and very readye at al times to ſerue and obey. The Captaines and Princes enter not into battayle, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remaine without, and cry with a lowde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>yce vnto their men, warning and ſteng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hening them, and from thence they prouide diligently what is conuenient to be done. Somtimes they ſet vpon horſes their ſonnes and wiues, and alſo the Images of men to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>creaſe their army, becauſe it ſhould ſeeme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> greater, and that it might be the more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onderfull and terrible to their enemies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen they fight, if it ſeeme good to them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey let them runne away, and it is not euill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ought of: when they ſhould ſhoote their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>wes they ſtrippe their right arme naked, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d afterwarde ſhoote their arrowes with ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat ſtrength, that there is no kinde of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our can defend thenemies, but that it will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſe through. They go together and fight
<pb facs="tcp:174043:11"/> in ſquadrons, and alſo flye together, and then they wound their enemies, that follow them with mortall woundes of arrowes: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde when they ſee the ſmall number of theyr aduerſaries, ſodenlye they returne to battayle agayn, and then they ſhoote at them and their horſes, and when it is thought that they are ouercome, then chiefly they remaine with the victorie. When they will geue bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell to any countrey, they deuide their army, and ſet vpon them in all partes, that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſuccoured of any, and none of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiters can runne away, and ſo they haue alwaies victorie, and when they haue gotten it, they vſe the ſame with great pride and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie, not pardoning any that they take, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther children, women, nor olde folkes, they kill all without any difference, vnleſſe it be the handy crafts men, whom they reſerue for their worke, and ſuch as they determine to kill, they deuide them among their pety cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, who appoynt to euerye one of their ſeruaunts ten, that ſo they may kill them, or more or leſſe, as the number requireth, and when all are put to death with a hatchet like pygges, that all others ſhould be terrified, they take of euery thouſand man one, &amp; this manner they hang vpon a peece of wood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174043:11"/> thoſe that are dead, with his hed down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, that it may ſeme that he geueth war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and aduice to the other. They keepe neither fayth nor promiſe with any, what ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer they haue promiſed, and much more cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eltie they vſe againſt ſuch as do render and yeelde them ſelues vnto them. The young women that they take captiues, they maye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe them at theyr pleaſure, and they carrye with them all ſuch as they like well of and put them to all ſubiection and ſlauerie, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake them to ſerue in bondage and miſerie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s long as they liue: theſe <hi>Tartars</hi> are the moſt vicious men of all the worlde, &amp; though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey take al the wyues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they liſt, or are able <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> keepe, no degree of affinitie or kinred can l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t them but that they mary with any at their pleaſure, except onelye the mother and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ughter: yet for all this they are very vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, no more nor leſſe then the <hi>Saraſens,</hi> &amp; <hi>Moores.</hi> And the wife which they take, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lde her not for theyr lawfull wiſe, neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they receiue her dowrie, vntil ſhe bring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rth children: and therfore it is lawfull b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them to put away ſuch as are barren, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> haue no children, and to take an other in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r ſteede. And it is to be wondred at, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>it many women haue but one huſband, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey neuer fall out, vnles it be great maruel.
<pb facs="tcp:174043:12"/> Notwithſtanding that ſome of them be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred and made more of then others: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the goodman keepeth companie with one of his wiues, ſometimes with an other, but euery one haue their family and habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aſunder, and they liue very chaſt: for if they be taken in adulterie, as well the man as the woman by their law ſhall ſuffer death preſently. When the men haue no warres, they keepe their cattell, go a hunting, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe them ſelues in wraſtling, and do nothing els, all the reſt of their affayres remayneth in the charge and ouerſight of the women. They haue a care of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is neceſſary, for their foode, apparell, and all other thinges apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining to the houſe. Theſe people vſe many ſuperſtitions and witchcraftes: chiefly they take it for a haynous matter to caſt a knife into the fire, or touch the fire therewith, or take the meate out of the pot with a knife. There can no ſtraunger be admitted to the kinges preſence, though he be of great dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and haue waightye affayres with him, but firſt he muſt purge him ſelfe. And if anye mans feete do ſmell, and come into the place where the Emperour is, although he be any of the Captaines, forthwith he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to be ſlaine: and beſides this if any
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174043:12"/> when he is eating, take a mouthfull that hee cannot ſwallow, but is forced to vomit it, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately they runne all to him, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d make a hoale vnder the place where he is, and that way they plucke him out and kill him cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. There are many other thinges that theſe holde for ſinne, without redemption: and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpects they account it a ſmall matter to kill men, to take other mens landes, and to rob the goodes of others againſt al right and iuſtice, and ſet light by the commandements of God, and with all this they beleeue that they ſhall liue after this life, for euer in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worlde: but they knowe not how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it, and beleeue that there they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue rewarde according to their deſertes. Immediately after that one of them falleth ſicke, and is neere the poynt of death, they take a launce and pich it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tent where he is, and ſet vpon the top of the ſame a blacke cloth, in token that none which paſſeth that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay ſhould enter in there: &amp; this being ſeene, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one dare go in, vnleſſe hee be called. And when the ſicke perſon is dead, all the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olde ioyne together, and take the body out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſhoppe or ſhedde, and carrieth it to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lace y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue appoynted for this cauſe: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> making there a hollow place, long and
<pb facs="tcp:174043:13"/> broad they rayſe vp a ſmall cotage or ſtall, and put a table therevppon full of meate, and ſet the deade body leaning to it, very richly apparelled, and ſo couer it alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with earth, they likewiſe bury with him one of his Cattell, and a Horſe with all thinges apperteining to him. And ſuche as are of moſte power and riches, when they are lyuing doe chooſe one of their ſeruaunts, and marke him with his Yron and marke, whome they cauſe to bee buryed with his maiſter, to the ende that in the other worlde they may haue one too doe them ſeruice. After this the friendes of the deceaſed, take an other Horſe, and kill him, and eate his fleſhe, and fill the ſkinne full of hay, and ſowing it togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, rayſe him vppe with foure peeces of timber, vppon the Sepulchre, in token that there is one buried, and the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men doe burne the bones, ſaying that they are for the purgation of the Soule. They which are of greateſt authoritie doe an other thing with the ſkinne: namely they cut it ſmall into very little ſtrings and ſtretching them round about the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, meaſure the earthe, and beleeue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174043:13"/> that the dead body ſhall haue ſo much in the other worlde, as his friendes do meaſure, with his ſkinne, and at the 30. dayes ende, they make an ende of their crying and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation. There are of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> certaine that are Chriſtians, although con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to true chriſtianitie. Theſe take after their fathers, when they waxe olde, becauſe they ſhould dye the ſooner, &amp; make an end of themſelues, and after their deceaſes, burne them, and gather diligently the aſhes, which they keepe as a precious thing, and therewith dayly dreſſe their meate. And now it would be tedious to write any more of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as alſo perhaps to reade with what ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and ſolemnitie the <hi>Tartars</hi> doe chooſe their kinges. After that any king dyeth (I will ſhewe it you in fewe woordes,) all the Princes, Captains, and chiefe men, and all the people of the realme, aſſemble and meete together, in a place appointed for that cauſe, in the fieldes according to their cuſtome and manner, and then take him, to whome the realme ought to come, either by ſucceſſion, or election, and place him in a Throne and Chaire of Gold, and he ſitting downe, all the people with a loude voyce ſay in this maner,
<pb facs="tcp:174043:14"/> We pray thee, &amp; likewiſe wil &amp; commaund, thee to be our ſouereigne Lord. Whervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he aunſwereth: if you will haue me ſo, it is neceſſary y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you be redy to do any thing that I commaund you, &amp; come when I cal you, &amp; that you go whether ſo euer I ſend you. And any that I commaund you to kill, that forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it be done, and that you put and leaue all the kingdome in our handes. Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately all aunſwer: So we are content. Then the king ſaith, From hence forwarde I will you to vnderſtand that the word of my mouth be my ſword: all the people with great noyſe and gladneſſe confirme the ſame. Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly, the principal and chiefe men of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple take the king, and bring him down from the royall chayre, and cauſe him to ſit vppon the ground, vpon a felt layd abroade, and ſay vnto him theſe wordes: Looke vpwarde, and knowe God, and then looke downe vpon the-felt whervpon thou ſitteſt. Thou ſhalt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, if thou gouerne the Realme well, thou ſhalt haue all that thou wilt at thy will: and if thou gouerne it ill, thou ſhalt bee throwne down, and diſpoſſeſſed in ſuch ſort, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that thou ſhalt not remaine with this poore felte where vppon thou ſitteſt: and in ſaying this, they place him one of his wiues neere
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174043:14"/> to him, that is beſt beloued, and lifting them both vp with the felt, they ſalute and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence him, as Emperour of all the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and ſhe as Empreſſe. Then the new Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and Empreſſe are preſented with many gifts, by al the people y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are vnder their Empire, and then they bring before him all that the deſeaſed king left, the which the new Emperour partely deuideth among the princes of his Realme, and commaundeth the remaynder to be kept for him ſelfe, and ſo the election is finiſhed, and the aſſemblie diſmiſſed, and from that time forwarde, all thinges are in his handes and power, none can nor dare ſay, this is mine, nor, ſuch a ones, none can liue in any part of the realme but where he is appoynted. The Emperour him ſelfe appoynteth places of abode, to the chiefe Captaines, and they, to the captaines of thouſands, and theſe, to the <hi>Centurions,</hi> and the <hi>Centurions</hi> to the <hi>Corporals,</hi> and theſe to the other Lordes. The ſeale &amp; ſignet which the king of the <hi>Tartars</hi> vſeth, hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen God in heauen, and <hi>Cuicut Chaam</hi> in earth, the fortreſſe of God, and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of all men, he hath fiue very great and ſtrong armies, and fiue Captaines, with the which he deſtroyeth and keepeth in ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:174043:15"/> all his aduerſaries. Vnto the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of other nations, hee ſpeaketh verie ſeldome, and conſenteth not to haue them come before him, vnleſſe that they and the giftes they bring, (without the which they neyther may, nor can come to his preſence) bee firſte purified, and by certaine wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men appointed for that purpoſe, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing whereof he anſwereth them by third perſons, and as long as he ſpeaketh, they muſt heare and hearken kneeling vpon their knees, be they neuer ſo great, and in ſuch ſort they muſt giue eare, that they erre not in the woordes they ſpeake to him, and change no woordes, for it is not lawfull for any man to alter nor change the Emperours woordes, nor ſtande againſt any iudgement that hee hath geuen in any manner of cauſe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Hee, nor any prince of <hi>Tartaria,</hi> neuer drinketh publikely, except they which ſerue firſt ſing or play ſomthing vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an inſtrument before him. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noblemen ride abrod they carry ouer them a hatte vppon a long lance, which ſhadeth them, and their wiues haue the like. Theſe were the manners of the <hi>Tartars</hi> two hundreth yeeres paſt, and this was the maner of their liues, and about
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174043:15"/> this time they ouercame and brought in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to them the <hi>Georgians,</hi> which were chriſtians &amp; kept the lawes of the <hi>Greekes,</hi> theſe were neighboures to the <hi>Greekes</hi> and their dominion did extend very farre euen from the region of <hi>Paleſtina</hi> vnto the <hi>Caſpian</hi> mountaines, and had eighteene bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks and a Patriarcke Sea: at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning they were ſubiect to the patriarcke of Antioch: they were warlike people. Some of the women were alſo expert in the warres and exerciſed their weapons. When theſe <hi>Georgians</hi> woulde enter into battell, they accuſtomed to drinke a bottell of wine that they vſe to carry with them, and when they had drunke it, they ſette vppon their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies with more courage.</p>
            <p>The prieſtes gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues freely to vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and Simonie, they had greate ſtrife and hatred with the people of <hi>Armenia.</hi> Theſe <hi>Armenians,</hi> of whome we ſpeake, were alſo Chriſtians before the <hi>Tartars</hi> ouercame them, and brought them in ſubiection, and after that the <hi>Georgians</hi> were once ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, they ſwarued in many thinges and departed from the true fayth and manners of the catholike Church.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:174043:16"/>
            <p>They knowe not the day of the byrth of our Lorde, they keepe no holy dayes nor faſting dayes, nor the foure ſeaſons of the yeare, the Satterday before Eaſter day they did not faſt: For they affirme that the ſame day our Lord had ryſen neere to the euening. All the Frydayes after Eaſter and Whitſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide they eate fleſhe, and otherwiſe they faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted much, and began their Lent from the Sunday of Septuageſima ſo ſtraightly, that the Wedneſday and Fryday they wold eate no oyle, nor fiſhe, nor drinke wine: for they thought hee did ſinne more that dranke wine thoſe dayes, then he which did commit the ſinne of lecherie. They did not all wholy refrayne from all meates on the Munday. The Teweſday &amp; the Thurſday they made but one meale. The Wedneſday and fryday they eate nothing. The Saterday and Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day they did continually eate fleſh. They did admit children of two monethes olde to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the holy Sacrament. They kept cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Ceremonies of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> all their Prieſtes were vſurers, as the <hi>Georgians</hi> were, and gaue them ſelues much to the arte of Necromancie, and more to drinking then the laye people did. They tooke wiues, but as ſoone as any one of them died, none of them
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:174043:16"/> could marry againe. If any woman did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit adulterie, the Biſhop gaue licence that her huſband ſhould put hir away, and take an other. Fynally in xxx. articles the <hi>Georgians</hi> gaue to vnderſtand, that they were departed from the true Chriſtian religion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:174043:17"/>
            <head>Of the Countrie of Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia, and of the rude manners <hi>of the Scithians.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>CITHIA</hi> is a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that lyeth towardes the Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>crion or north, ſo called by <hi>Scitha,</hi> Sonne vnto <hi>Hercules,</hi> as <hi>Herodoto</hi> ſayth, or as <hi>Beroſo</hi> affirmeth of an other <hi>Scitha,</hi> Sonne to <hi>Araxes Priſca</hi> wife to <hi>Noe,</hi> who was borne in that countrie. Theſe <hi>Scithi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> at the beginning did poſſeſſe a ſmall countrey, vntill by little and little, by their valiantnes and ſtrength, they enlarged their Empire, bringing vnder their ſubiection many nations. Theſe people at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning made their abode neere to the riuer <hi>Araxes</hi> being very fewe in number, and litle eſteemed, vntill they had gotten a Martiall King excelling in the feates of armes, vnder whom they enlarged their countrie and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and it extendeth by that ſide where the mountaines lye vnto the Ocean Seas, and the lake <hi>Meotis</hi> paſſeth by diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vnto the riuer <hi>Tanais:</hi> from the which ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174043:17"/> 
               <hi>Scithia</hi> ſtretcheth in length. And at the eaſt ende it is deuided into two ſortes of people parted aſſunder almoſt in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the mountaine <hi>Ymao,</hi> the one of the which is called the <hi>Scithians</hi> within <hi>Ymao,</hi> and the other the <hi>Scithians</hi> without. The <hi>Scithians</hi> were neuer ſet vpon, or at the leaſt not ouercome of any other ſtrange empire. <hi>Darius</hi> king of the <hi>Perſians</hi> ſet vpon them, but in the ende returned flying away with great ſhame. They beheaded the king <hi>Cirus</hi> with all his armie, and deſtroyed a Captaine of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great with all his power, they hearde of the armies of the Romaines, but felt them not, they are a hard people and can ſuffer greate labour, &amp; warres, &amp; be very valiant, theſe people at the beginning did not go far one from another, for they neither vſed tillage, nor had any houſes nor abiding place, but ſoiourned in the deſerts &amp; moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, carrieng their beaſtes, and cattaile, wiues and children with them in cartes, they had no lawes, but obſerued Iuſtice and equitie by their owne accord. Among theſe there was no greater euill then theft, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing more puniſhed, and ſo it was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſeeing they had no houſes, nor enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for their cattaile, but all thinges lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade in the fieldes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:174043:18"/>
            <p>There was neyther golde nor ſiluer amonge them, neither knew they what it meant.</p>
            <p>Their meate which they vſed moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, was milke and hony. They cloathed their bodies againſt the colde and froſt with the ſkinnes of wilde beaſtes, and rats. The vſe of wooll and apparell was not knowne among them.</p>
            <p>This was the manner of liuing vſed, and common for the moſt part among the <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> but not generally of all: for as ſome of them were farre of from the reſt, by diſtaunce of places, ſo likewiſe they differ in their liues, and had peculiar cuſtomes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them ſelues, of the which we wil ſpeak after we haue declared the manners of the common ſorte of people. The moſt parte of the <hi>Scithians</hi> reioyce to kil men, wherevpon they haue taken a cuſtome to drink the blood of the firſt man that any of them taketh pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in battaile, he drinketh blood, and of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one that any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> killeth, he preſenteth the heades to the king, and for cutting off of the ſame, is partaker of any thing of value that is found about him, and otherwiſe not. They cut of the head in this ſorte, they take the ſkull and caſt out al that is in it, and take of the ſkin, and make it ſoft with their hands
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:174043:18"/> as the ſkinne of a cowe, and ſo keepe it as a precious thing, and put it in the raines of their horſes, and of this they triumph much: for he that hath moſt of theſe is accompted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he worthieſt and valianteſt man. There are many of them that ſowe the ſkinnes of men together, as though they were ſkinnes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſtes, and vſe them for coueringes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of them vſe to pluck of the ſkinne from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e right handes of their enemies with their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayles, and therwith couer the quiuer of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rowes. An other ſort fleyeth the men, and caſteth their ſkins vpon wood, and after put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em vpon horſes, and the heades being cut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, as we haue already declared, they couer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſkul with the raw ſkin of an oxe, and gild <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on the in ſide, and vſe to drink in the ſame. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſometimes when gueſts come to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uſes, they bring forth thoſe cups, and ſhew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w thoſe men were ouercome by them, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is they account a worthy matter. Once a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare all the Princes of thoſe Regions do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anquet their neighbours, and all ſuch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell neere vnto them with wine, in thoſe Cuppes, whereof they all drinke, that haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lled any of their enemies with their owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>andes, and he that hath killed none in that
<pb facs="tcp:174043:19"/> ſorte, taſteth not of the ſame, but without ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is ſet aſide by him ſelfe from the reſt of the company, which is taken among them for a matter of great ſhame and reproch, and ſuch as haue killed many drinke with two cuppes together. The Gods vnto whome they pray &amp; geue honour, are the Goddeſſe <hi>Veſta</hi> chiefly, and then <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe <hi>Tellus:</hi> For they thinke that the earth is wife to <hi>Iupiter.</hi> After theſe they honour <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo,</hi> and the celeſtial <hi>Venus,</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> and <hi>Hercules:</hi> but their opinion is that they may not make any Intage of any of them, nor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, nor Churches, but to the God <hi>Mars</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vnto whome they offer in ſacrifice one of euery hundred of their captiues. And to their other Goddeſſes they offer other beaſtes, and eſpecially horſes: Swine they eſteeme not of, neyther will haue any in their countrie.</p>
            <p>When the king giueth out a commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to put any perſon to death, for any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or cauſe, he appoynteth all his ſonnes to be ſlaine with him, but there is no hurt done to the women children. The leagues and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie that the <hi>Scithians</hi> enter into in their warres are in this ſort. They take a greater-then veſſell, whervnto they powre wine with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174043:19"/> the blood of ſuch as ſhall ioyne in friendſhip to them, wounding them ſelues with ſome knife, or cutting ſome place of their body. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that in the ſame veſſell they wette their ſwords and arrowes, halbards, and launces, and then coniure &amp; curſe with many wordes, and immediately drinke that wine, not onely all ſuch as enter into theſe leagues, but alſo their aſſociates and companions, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe that are of greateſt degree. The Sepulchres and Tombes of their kinges are neere to the cittie called <hi>Gerros,</hi> where the Ryuer <hi>Boriſteneus</hi> beginneth, to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igable, and euen there, as ſoone as the king is dead, they digge a great ſquare hole, and then take the body, and open it, and take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut the bowelles, and make them cleane, the which they fyll vp with the ſmall bowes of a willow tree, beaten to powder, and of <hi>Thimiamo,</hi> and with the ſeede of <hi>Apio,</hi> and Anniſe ſeede, and immediately ſowe it vp againe, and laye it in a cart, and ſo carrye him from one countrey to an other, and whereſoeuer they receiue him, they do the like: but ſuch as are of kindred to the king do cut of his eares, and alſo his hayre round about, they geue his armes many
<pb facs="tcp:174043:20"/> ſmall cuttes, and wound his forehead &amp; noſe, they ſhoote throw his left hand with arrowes and after this they carry the kinges body vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other people of his Empyre, who accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany him vntill they returne where the firſt came forth, and after they haue carryed him among all his people from countrie to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, they lay him among them that dwell in the vttermoſt partes of the Realme, where the Sepulchres of the kinges are, and after they haue put him into a place which is made vpon the Sepulchre, they ſhut him vp with lances made faſt from one ſide to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and prepare good ſtore of wood, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him with a cloke, and in the other ſide of the Sepulchre, they cut the throtes of his woman which was beſt beloued of al, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of a ſeruaunt, a cooke, a driuer of Aſſes, a poſt, a page, &amp; a horſe. They bury him with certeine cuppes of golde, and with the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal of all other things, and after a yeare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired they do the like, killing alwayes the kinges chiefe ſeruaunts. Theſe ſeruaunts of the kinges are the moſt principal of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Scithia:</hi> for there is no ſlaue admitted to the kinges ſeruice. Of theſe they cut the throtes of fiftie, and of as many horſes of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174043:20"/> moſt excellente, and after taking out the bowels, and hauing garmentes, and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings ſtitched togither, they take the horſes and rayſe them vp on their feete in a place made hollowe round about the Kings Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, and vppon them they place the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes ſitting, and ſet them in ſuch order, that afarre off they ſeeme like to a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of men on horſebacke that tarryed for the King. In this ſort they vſe the bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als and Sepulchres of their kings. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ſuch as are next in degree to the king, and alſo the comon people haue their manner and faſhion in their buryals: for as ſoone as one dyeth, the next of his kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes lay him in a carte, and carry him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his friends, from one to another, and euery one by him ſelfe receiueth him, and maketh great feaſtes, as well to the kinred as to others that accompany the dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. In this ſort they carry him fortie dayes and after bury him, taking out firſt all that is in his head, and waſhing it, and vpon the body they put three pieces of timber, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one to the other round about him, vpon the which they hang certeine woll. The men of <hi>Scithia</hi> waſh not them ſelues, but the women waſh their bodyes with water,
<pb facs="tcp:174043:21"/> and rub them ſelues with a plain ſtone ſhut within a peece of wood of Cypres, or Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or ince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe. After they haue ſo waſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, that they begin to ſmel, they annoynt all their body &amp; face with oyntments, &amp; ſo they remaine very cleane &amp; ſhining. The maner of the othe that they ſweare, is by the kings chayr. And if they find any periured, which they knowe by the diuines, that haue the knowledge therof, immediatly without any longer tarrying, they behead him, and he loſeth all his goods, which is giuen to ſuch as accuſed him of periury. There are in <hi>Scithia</hi> other people called the <hi>Maſſagetas</hi> towards the part of <hi>Aſia</hi> neere to the <hi>Caſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> ſea, which are like to the people of <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia</hi> in apparell, &amp; alſo in life, by the which many beleeue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are <hi>Scithians.</hi> Theſe fight both on horſeback &amp; on foote, &amp; eyther way are almoſt inuincible. In battayle they vſe arrowes &amp; launces, &amp; ſhort ſwords that they always carry with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They vſe much gold in their girdels, &amp; in the trimming of their heads, &amp; vnder their armepits, &amp; in the breaſts of their horſes. The heades of their launces &amp; arrowes be of copper. There is neither Iron nor ſiluer among them. Euery of them taketh out wife, but afterward ſhee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174043:21"/> is common to all. Howe long they liue, no man hitherto could ſet downe any certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: for as ſoone as any of them beginneth to waxe olde, his kinſfolkes and friendes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eete together and kill him, and then ſeethe him, and after ſacrifice him with certeyne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heepe, and then eate of that fleſhe at a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et which they make. And this manner of death they accompt a happy kind of death. And if he dye of any diſeaſe, they eate him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot, but rather bury him, &amp; hold it for a gret ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me &amp; loſſe that he was not killed &amp; ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed. They ſowe nothing in the earth, but liue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the cattel, &amp; fiſhes that are taken in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uer <hi>Araxes,</hi> and for the moſt parte drinke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilke. They worſhip the Sunne, and to it they offer ſacrifice w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> horſes, ſaying it is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ighteſt planet, &amp; therfore the lighteſt beaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight to be ſacrifiſed to him. There is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her ſort of people called <hi>Seres,</hi> who are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong themſelues very quiet &amp; tame, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from the company of al men, in ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat they wil haue no trafique w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any ſtrange <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eople. Howbeit merchants may paſſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir riuer, &amp; in the ſame without any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ling put their merchandize to exchange, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that they buy nothing, but by way of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y exchange one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie for another.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:174043:22"/>
            <p>Among this laſt ſort, there is no woman brought to anſwer in iudgement nor other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe touched, although ſhee be a wicked woman, an adultereſſe, or theefe. And as it is reported, there hath beene no man put to death among them at any time: for the feare &amp; reuerence which they haue to their lawes, is of more ſtrength then any other conſtellation or ſinne. They dwell at the beginning of the roundneſſe of the worlde, and becauſe they liue chaſte, they be not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with Caterpiller nor worme, nor hayle, nor peſtilence, nor any other euils. The woman after ſhee is conceiued, is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther touched nor deſired of any. Vncleane fleſhe or forbidden, none eate thereof. Euery one is Iudge for him ſelfe, according to the righteouſnes of Iuſtice, and therefore they are not chaſtened nor afflicted with thoſe plagues that are vſed to come to others for their ſinnes, and ſo they liue long, and ende their life without any diſeaſe. There are others which are called <hi>Tauroſcythas</hi> of the mountayne <hi>Tauro,</hi> neare to the which they inhabite. Theſe offer in ſacrifice to the virgin <hi>Ephigenia</hi> all thoſe that come ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to them by ſea, and are loſt, and al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Greekes</hi> that repaire thither, and the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174043:22"/> ſacrifice is in this manner. After they haue made certein prayers, they wound the head of the man, and ſo kill him. Others ſay, they caſt the body headlong from a great rocke, becauſe her temple ſtandeth vpon a high rocke, and they ſet the head vpon a ſtake. And ſome ſay, that the body is not caſt downe from the rocke, but that they bury it. This diuell to whome they offer this ſacrifice, they ſay is <hi>Ephigenia,</hi> that was daughter to king <hi>Agamemnon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their enimies whome they take they vſe in this ſort: euery one cutteth off the head of his enimie, and carryeth it to his houſe, and ſetteth it vpon a ſtaffe, the greateſt that he can get, and then ſetteth it vpon his houſe, &amp; commonly vppon the chimney, and ſay that they ſet them ſo high, to the ende their eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies may be keepers of all the houſe. They of this cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey liue by robberies &amp; warres. There are others called <hi>Agatirſos,</hi> which are very politike, &amp; vſe to weare vpon their bodies great ſtore of golde. All their wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are common among them, for they ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey are al brethren, &amp; of one houſe. There is not among them any enuye, nor contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, but are like in manners to the people of <hi>Tracia.</hi> There are others called <hi>Neuros,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:174043:23"/> which vſe the maners and lawes of the <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians.</hi> Theſe were conſtrayned to leaue their countrey one yeare before the conqueſt of king <hi>Darius,</hi> by reaſon of the multitude of Serpentes that breede in it. They holde for a certaine trueth, and ſweare, that euery yeare in certeine dayes they were conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Wolues, and afterwarde returned into the forme and ſhape that they were firſt of. There are others which are called <hi>Antropophagis</hi> becauſe they eate mens fleſh, whoſe manners and lawes are the moſte rude and beaſtly of all others, which are among men. They liue vnder no maner of lawe. All their trade is in cattell. Their apparel is like to theirs of <hi>Scithia.</hi> They haue a language proper to them ſelues. Ther are other called <hi>Melandenos,</hi> which vſe to weare all their apparell blacke, and therefore are ſo called. Theſe onely among the <hi>Scithians</hi> do eate mans fleſhe: In the reſt they haue the manners and lawes of the people of <hi>Scithia.</hi> The <hi>Budinos</hi> are ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great nation, and all theſe haue fayre eyes, and the collours of their bodyes are white and red. The citie that theſe poſſeſſe is called <hi>Gelona,</hi> of the which they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Gelonas,</hi> and this is the head place of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:174043:23"/> that realme. They make their feaſtes in the honour of the god <hi>Bacchus,</hi> which are called <hi>Trietericas Bacchanales,</hi> from three yeares to three yeares. Theſe were <hi>Greeks</hi> in tymes paſt, but going out of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, came to this region, where they made their abode, and euen at this daye, vſe parte of the <hi>Greeke</hi> language, and part of the <hi>Scithians.</hi> The <hi>Budinos</hi> do differ from the <hi>Gelones</hi> in their language &amp; life: for theſe <hi>Budinos</hi> are naturalles of this countrey, and al their liuing dependeth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the trade of cattell, and theſe of that regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vſe to eate lyce. <hi>Gelones</hi> are labourers and tillers of the earth, and haue corne, and poſſeſſe gardeines and orchardes, and haue no manner of likeneſſe at all vnto the <hi>Budi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos,</hi> neither in countenance nor collour: all the realme where theſe inhabite is full of trees, by a very great lake that is there.</p>
            <p>They hunt great ſtore of wilde beaſts. And of their ſkinnes make gownes for them ſelues to weare. There is an other kynde of people called <hi>Argipeos,</hi> which liue at the foote of certeine high mountaines. They are a people balde from the tyme of their birth, as well the women as the men.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:174043:24"/>
            <p>They haue flat and broad noſes, and verye great beardes and a certayne ſounde of a voyce wherewith they ſpeake. They are apparelled like to the <hi>Scythians.</hi> They liue commonly of the fruite of trees. They care not for breeding of cattell, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue not many. Euery one hath his dwelling place vnder a tree, which in the Winter they couer with a white couering, and in the Summer it is not couered at all. No people of the worlde hurteth them, for they ſay that they are ſanctified. They poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe no armour, neither to defende, nor to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend: but rather themſelues by perſwaſions and faire meanes, take vp all maner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies &amp; ſtrifes that riſe among them. Whoſoeuer commeth vnto them, they fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and ſuccour him. There are others called <hi>Iſledones,</hi> which vſe theſe cuſtomes: whenſoeuer the father of any of them dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, all his kinred bring thither their cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, the which they kill and make bankets, and the like is done of the father of him that hath conuited them, and ſo they make their banket, eating the fleſhe of the dead man, with the fleſh of the cattaile. They flea and take off the ſkinne of the head of the dead man, and clenſe it of all that is therwithin,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:174043:24"/> and after gilde the ſame, &amp; haue it for their image, and make therevnto euery yeare very great ceremonies, and ſacrifices. This the father doeth for the ſonne, and the ſonne for the father, euen as the <hi>Greekes</hi> do cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the day of their birth. Theſe do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme them ſelues to be a iuſt people, and their women are as ſtrong as the men the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Theſe were the manners and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Scithians</hi> in tymes paſt, vntill they were brought vnder the ſubiection of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and then followed their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of liuing, and nowe liue as the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> do, being all called <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> by one gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall name.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:174043:25"/>
            <head>Of the Countrie that is called, the other ſide of Ganges, and of Cataya, and the region of Sinas, which <hi>is a countrey of the great Cham; and of</hi> the meruailous things that haue bene ſeene in thoſe countries.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eyond the riuer <hi>Ganges</hi> towards the Eaſt, is the land and part of <hi>India,</hi> that ſtandeth on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide of the ſame ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and therfore is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the other ſide of <hi>Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</hi> This is the greateſt, the beſt, &amp; the ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt countrey of all <hi>India,</hi> which is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Eaſt partes, where the Sunne riſeth, and is now called <hi>Cataya,</hi> and it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth to the great <hi>Cham,</hi> who is lorde of <hi>Tartaria.</hi> In old time it was ſaide, that it belonged to <hi>Preſter Iohn.</hi> The countrey of <hi>Cataya</hi> is greate, and hath in it manye kingdomes, and the buyldings like to <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi> There is in it great policie of all things. It is a riche countrey of Gold, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and precious ſtones, whereof there is great aboundance. The people are of great
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174043:25"/> reaſon, and liue in better order then we do. There are among them Philoſophers, who are much eſteemed: The ſeconde ſort are huſbandmen: The third Shepheards: The fourth, handicraftes men: The fifth, men of warre to defende the countrey: The ſixt, the preſidents and gouernours, that gouerne the country: The ſeuenth, are the counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers to the king. And theſe are cheefeſt, and haue charge ouer all the reſt, and will not conſent that any one ſhould leaue his owne office or ſcience, and take an other, and therefore they are better gouerned then we are. The great <hi>Chain</hi> deuyded this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince into nine kingdomes, in the which are two thouſande great cities, or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts. There is no richer prouince in the worlde. It hath all thinges neceſſarie, and in great plentie for the life of mankinde. The <hi>Catayans</hi> are idolaters, great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes, and craftes men. They giue them ſelues much to Aſtronomy. There are among them many religious houſes of Idolaters, which leade a ſtraight life.</p>
            <p>They haue among them there Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and ſtudies of learning, and the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the old and newe Teſtament, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it commeth to paſſe that they honor God,
<pb facs="tcp:174043:26"/> and beleeue in the euerlaſting life, but are not baptized. They loue the Chriſtians and giue almes, with a good will. They haue no beardes. They are much like in face &amp; countenaunce to thoſe of the prouince of <hi>Mongall.</hi> There are many Chriſtians in <hi>Cataya.</hi> It is ſo great a countrey, and ſo inhabited, that in a verye ſhort ſpace the great <hi>Cham</hi> can ioyne together an armye of three hundred thouſand fighting men. In the prouince of <hi>Cataya</hi> they haue no wine, but make their drinke of Riſe. They haue fleſhe, milke, and cheeſe. They bury their dead bodyes richely. In this prouince they celebrate their weddings with great ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, Songs, and Trumpets. They vſe bathes. They deuide the yeare into 12 monethes, according to the twelue ſignes. The moſte part of theſe people accompteth the yeare from Auguſt. They vſe Croſſe-bowes, and gunnes, and of all kinde of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery, for they are the beſt handycraftes men in the worlde. They write vppon the leaues of trees, and make bookes of them. They make money of the rinds of Mulbery trees. In ſome places they vſe ſmall Irons for money, like to needles: In other places ſmall peeces of Golde. There is among
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:174043:26"/> theſe neither peſtilence, nor any other conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious diſeaſes, and therefore is ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of people. There is in this countrey many and very great Serpents, which the <hi>Catayans</hi> do eate in their ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets with great affection. The princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall citie in <hi>Cataya</hi> is <hi>Cambula,</hi> contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning xxiiii. myles in compaſſe, and is foure ſquare, and in euery ſquare reacheth vi. myles. Some ſaye that it contayneth xl. Italian myles, which is xx. leagues in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe. The walles are xx. paces in height, and v. in breadth, with pinacles vpon all of three paces in height. In the foure corners are foure rounde fortes, and euery one of them foure myles in compaſſe, with greate prouiſion of armour in euery of the ſame.</p>
            <p>This citie hath xii. gates, two myles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant one from another. Euery gate hath ouer it a faire large houſe, wherein are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually a thouſand watchmen kept to gard the citie. There is a wall that goeth to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of theſe fortes, with their arches, where the king may paſſe into any of them. The great <hi>Cham</hi> his pallace is ſtrong and very ſtately and faire. The ſtreetes are ſtreight, in ſo much that the light of the fire is ſeene from one ende to another. In this
<pb facs="tcp:174043:27"/> citie are many faire and ſumptuous houſes, and palaces, and in the middeſt of it, is a great and wonderfull Pallace, with a high tower therein, wherevpon there is a great bell, and when it ringeth in the night, none dare walke abroad in the ſtreates, but the watchemen of the citie, and Midwiues, and Phiſicions, who muſt paſſe with light. And without the citie are twelue great ſtreates, euery one aunſwering to his gate of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, wherein there are many craftes men and merchants dwelling: and in the ſame are lodged all ſuch as come to the court a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout any buſines: and the Stewes are kept in thoſe ſtreates, in the which are aboue xx. thouſand women of euil liuing, and not one of them dare enter into the citie vpon paine of burning. Out of this citie goeth euery day more then a thouſand cartes laden with ſilke. Nere to the citie of <hi>Cambalu</hi> there is a mountayne, wherein are founde blacke ſtones which burne like vnto drye wood.</p>
            <p>There is alſo nere to <hi>Cataya</hi> a countrey of xx. days iourney, inhabited with Chriſtians <hi>Neſtorians,</hi> which haue greater &amp; fayrer churches then we haue. In this citie of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balu</hi> the great <hi>Cham</hi> hath his Pallace and Court, which is very great. And it is ſayde,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:174043:27"/> that this Pallace hath 4. Columnes of fine gold, and the walles of the Pallace layde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer with golde, and the floores layed with brickes of gold &amp; ſiluer. In this Pallace are the great <hi>Cham</hi> his wiues, which are foure in nomber of lawfull birth, euery of which hath in her court thirtie thouſand maides, &amp; many pages, men &amp; women that ſerue them which are more then foure thouſand men &amp; women. His eldeſt ſonne of his firſt wife hath his court by him ſelfe. There watche euery night xx. thouſande gentlemen on horſebacke, which are his garde: And foure thouſand perſons ſit at meat with him. The firſt wife ſitteth at his left hande, &amp; the reſt ſucceſſiuely: and at his other hande ſit his ſonnes, &amp; his ſonnes ſonnes, euery one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his age. He hath xx. thouſande huntſmen, &amp; foure thouſand dogs, &amp; xx. thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand hawkes, &amp; fiue thouſand Gerfalcons, &amp; a great nomber of Acorres. They pitch ten thouſand tents in the fieldes, when he goeth to his paſtimes of hunting. And two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall tents for him ſelf, wherin may be two thouſand knights at pleaſure, the which te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are furniſhed with ſuch riches, that one of the ſmall realmes is not able to buy them. The great <hi>Cham</hi> is the greateſt Lord of
<pb facs="tcp:174043:28"/> the whole earth, and ſo intitleth him ſelfe king of kinges, and lorde of lordes, and in trueth, he is lorde from <hi>Scythia,</hi> euen tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe out all the Eaſt partes, &amp; from thence to the <hi>Mediteran</hi> Sea: ſo that not without reaſon he cauſeth him ſelfe to be written, lorde and Emperour of all the Eaſt partes. He commaundeth him ſelfe to be called the ſonne of God, and in this gloryeth much. He hath great countryes and very riche, &amp; thereby is the greateſt lorde, and the richeſt of the worlde, as we haue already rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. In the Winter, the <hi>Tartars</hi> come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the plaine feeldes, which are hote and of good paſture, and in the Sommer they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde in the mountaynes, and among the trees, and freſh places. They make rounde houſes of tymber &amp; couer them with felts, and theſe houſes they carry with them w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſoeuer they goe. And alwayes they ſet the dore of the houſe in the Sommer time towardes the South, and in the Winter towardes the North. They bring likewiſe ſome cartes couered with feltes, ſo ſtrong, that the water neuer paſſeth thorow them, the which are drawen with Camels. Vpon theſe they carry their wiues, children, &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. All the other cuſtomes and manners
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:174043:28"/> of the <hi>Tartars</hi> are ſpoken of already, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e treated of <hi>Tartaria.</hi> The prouince of <hi>Mangi</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Mongall</hi> is neare vnto <hi>Cataya,</hi> &amp; ſubiect to the great <hi>Cham.</hi> It hath vnder the iuriſdiction thereof eight realmes, and in euery realme a 140. cities. And in all the prouince of <hi>Mangi</hi> is a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand two hundred and two cities, very great and riche. There is in this countrey great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rade of clothes of golde, and ſilke, and of precious ſtones, &amp; pearles, and of all ſortes of ſpices. The people are for the moſt parte all handycraftes men. They cauſe the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to followe their fathers occupations. There are a great nomber that vſe the ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Necromancie, and witchecraft: and there are many euil people, and of wicked conditions. There is in this countrey no man of warre, nor horſe for the warres, by reaſon it is ſituated in a ſtrong place, and ſhut vp with many waters: and round about the cities and townes are deepe and broade <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aues full of water. The people of this countrey are much toubled with ſickeneſſe, and diſeaſes. If they gaue them ſelues to ſeates of armes, all the world coulde not bring the prouince of <hi>Mangi</hi> vnder ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They worſhip idols: they ſpeake the
<pb facs="tcp:174043:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:174043:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:174043:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:174043:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:174043:31"/> 
               <hi>Perſian</hi> language: they burn their dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. They vſe in this countrie money of Corall, and the women bring it hanging at their neckes, and deck their Idols with it, &amp; therefore it is much deſired and ſet by. In this prouince they make clothes of golde &amp; ſilke, and chamblet in very great quantitie. There are in this prouince maſtiues, as great as Aſſes. All they that are borne in the prouince of <hi>Mangi</hi> haue the day &amp; houre of their birthes written, that the lord of the countrey may knowe it. When any man will take his iourney, he goeth to aſke coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the diuines. When they dye they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell their bodies in canuas, &amp; burne them with papers wherein are paynted diuels, horſes, ſlaues, beaſtes, and apparell. And they ſay, that all the ſame ſhall ſerue thoſe that dye in another worlde. And when they burne the bodyes, they ſing and make much mirth, and ſaye that the goddes do ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them with ioye in the other worlde.</p>
            <p>There are many great &amp; riche cities in the prouince of <hi>Cataya</hi> &amp; <hi>Mangi,</hi> as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple one called <hi>Gengomſu,</hi> being ten miles in compaſſe, and the walles of the pallace of that citie, are round about on the inſide lined with golde. In the prouince of <hi>Mangi</hi> is another citie called <hi>Nocian,</hi> ſubiect alſo
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:174043:31"/> to the great <hi>Cham,</hi> where men haue their teeth couered with golde, &amp; the women ſet great ſtore by their hayre, and buy &amp; ſell, &amp; gouerne all the goods, and the men followe no kinde of buſines, but apply their hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, &amp; pleaſure, &amp; paſtimes in the feeldes, &amp; go to the warres. And when the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue brought forth their children, the men go to bed &amp; take the child &amp; keepe it vntil fourtie dayes be paſt, &amp; the women riſe vp &amp; go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, as though they had not ben deliuered of any child &amp; ſerue their huſbands. <hi>Singni</hi> is alſo a great and noble citie, contayning fourtie miles in compaſſe, and in it is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of people, &amp; al are Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, Phiſicions, merchants &amp; handy craftes men, very expert in all artes. Ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re in this citie vii. thouſand ſtone bridges, brought very curiouſly, vnder the which, a Galley may rowe very wel. In the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of this citie groweth Rewbarb and Ginger, in great abundance. There are wrought in it many clothes of gold &amp; ſilke, of ſundry coulours, the citizens reioycing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch to apparell themſelues therewith. And fiue days iourney beyond it, is the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble citie of <hi>Quinſay,</hi> which is as much to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye, as the citie of Heauen, and it is the
<pb facs="tcp:174043:32"/> head citie in the prouince of <hi>Mangi.</hi> It is reported to conteine in compaſſe one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred miles, and to haue twelue thouſand bridges of ſtone, with arches ſo high, that a great ſhip may paſſe vnder. This citie is ſituate in the water, like <hi>Venis,</hi> and euery one dwelling therein followeth the occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his father and aunceſtours. There is in this citie a lake xxx. myles in compaſſe, and in the ſame lake ſtande the beſt palla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the worlde, eſpecially in the middeſt thereof be two, wherein are made all the mariage feaſtes of the citie: and they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes furniſhed and trimmed for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages. In this citie they vſe the money of <hi>Tartaria,</hi> which is of the rinde of a Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery tree. Vppon euery one of thoſe bridges there be always watchemen readie, to the ende there ſhould no harme be done, nor any tumult or rebellion ariſe in the citie. There are in it xiiii. bathes. The gret <hi>Cham</hi> doth ſet great ſtore by this citie. In the ſame there is a great &amp; faire pallace of the kings, made foure ſquare, and compaſſed about with walles ten myles, with verye faire chambers and other roomes, and gardeins, and fountayns, and a great pond with much fiſh. There is alſo in this citie an honorable
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:174043:32"/> church of Chriſtians <hi>Neſtorians.</hi> Of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Quinſaye</hi> &amp; of his prouince the great <hi>Cham</hi> doth receiue foure thouſand and fiue hundred hanegs of golde, and euery ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neg is 126. thouſande duccats and aboue, &amp; this onely is receiued of ſalt. Of his other rents he receiueth euery yeare ten thouſand hanegs of golde. In this courſe neare to <hi>Ganges</hi> is a countrey that is called the golden <hi>Cherſoneſo,</hi> the which is in the <hi>Equinoctiall,</hi> and runneth ouerthwart, and ſtandeth from <hi>Melaca</hi> foure hundreth and fiftie leages. All this countrey is verye riche, and hath great aboundance of golde, and therefore it was ſo called, or becauſe it ſeemeth that the Sunne riſeth gilded, and ſhining. And beyond that, more then 500. leages lyeth the Iland of <hi>Ciampa</hi> or <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ampago,</hi> as <hi>Marcus Paulus</hi> calleth it. It is a great Iland, and very aboundant of gold and precious ſtones. The king of this Iland hath his pallaces all couered with planches of golde for tyles, and the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and marbles of the pallace are all of golde. All the trees of this Iland are of a ſweete ſmel: there is in it much white pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. The people of this Iland are faire peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but euil in manners, for they are Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters:
<pb facs="tcp:174043:33"/> they worſhip Idols, &amp; figures pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in diuerſe ſortes. They kill their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, eate their fleſh, and drink their blood. They ſpeake the <hi>Perſian</hi> tongue. Neare to this Iland are many others which are in nomber aboue ſeuen thouſande foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth, as they report that haue ſayled in thoſe partes. From <hi>Ciampa</hi> vnto <hi>Iaua</hi> the great, are 150. leages. <hi>Iaua</hi> hath in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe three thouſand myles: there are in it ſeuen crowned kings. It is an Iland verye rich of golde, and hath very great ſtore of victuals: and there is in the ſame greate plentie of Cinamon, cloues, pepper, and ginger, and many other ſpices in great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance. The people are Idolaters, they ſpeake the <hi>Perſian</hi> language. <hi>Iaua</hi> the leſſe hath 200. miles in compaſſe: there are in it eight kings: they ſpeake the <hi>Perſian</hi> tongue: they worſhip idols: they haue lack of all kind of victuals. Eyght leages from <hi>Iaua</hi> towardes the Southweſt is another Iland which is called <hi>Iocat,</hi> great &amp; ryche. There is in it great abundance of golde, and many Elefants and Apes, and manye ſmall ſnayles, of the which, they vſe the ſhelles for money. And as they write from <hi>Ophir,</hi> from whence <hi>Salomon</hi> cauſed gold
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:174043:33"/> to be caryed for the Temple of Ieruſalem, it is beleeued to be the ſame: for in it is great abundaunce of golde, and of all other things which were carryed to <hi>Salomon.</hi> And thirtie leages from <hi>Iaua</hi> the leſſe, is the <hi>Gatigara</hi> nyne or ten degrees from the Equinocciall on the other ſide towardes the South. Beyond this there is no other countrey knowen, by reaſon there hath ben no nauigation any further fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe partes: and by land it cannot be trauailed, for the great number of lakes and high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, which be there. And it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported that the earthly Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize lyeth that way.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:174043:34"/>
            <head>Of many notable things that are found in the land of Tartaria, and in the Eaſt India.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Yke as the gatherer of grapes, after he hath ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered all that he can, &amp; made his principall ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering in: yet after that he cauſeth the refuſe to be gathered, &amp; maketh an after gathering. Euen ſo it will hap to mee in this worke: for at the concluſion I will not let to ſeeke agayne, if there be any notable thing to be found in theſe <hi>Indias</hi> and prouinces of the Eaſt partes, which haue not beene ſpoken of: and in the ſetting downe thereof, will keepe no other order, then to begin by the deſcription and diuiſion of <hi>India,</hi> the which <hi>Pogio Florentino</hi> left written by the infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of one <hi>Nicholas</hi> a <hi>Venecian</hi> that trauailed thoſe partes and ſawe them.</p>
            <p>All <hi>India</hi> is deuided into three partes. The firſt part is from the region of <hi>Perſia,</hi> vnto the riuer <hi>Indo.</hi> The ſecond part is the middeſt from the riuer <hi>Indo,</hi> vnto the riuer
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:174043:34"/> 
               <hi>Ganges.</hi> The thirde, called the fartheſt and laſt, is from <hi>Ganges</hi> vnto the ende of that which is knowen to be inhabited: and this exceedeth much the other in policy, riches, and good lawes. For it is certeine, that the men of this <hi>India</hi> haue ſumptuous houſes, and well wrought, and all things appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to them very cleane and handſome.</p>
            <p>There are very riche merchauntes which haue tables and table clothes, and cupbords of plate as we haue: and many of them are not without fourtie ſhips of their owne, for their affaires, that euery one of them is eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teemed to be worth 80. thouſand duccates. All theſe lacke bread and wine. They liue by Rice, fleſh, milk, and cheeſe, &amp; alſo make their drinke with Rice grounde &amp; mingled with water: they make it a ſhyning red coulour with the iuyce of a certeyne kind of tree. They haue great abundance of hennes Capons, Partriges, Feyſants, and other birdes, and wilde fowle, and ſleepe in beds trimmed with golde, &amp; couered with quilts of cotten woll. They weare alſo clothes of linnen, &amp; ſarge, tyed together with ſtringes of crimſon and golde. The women vſe to weare ſhowes of thin leather paynted with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>de and ſilke, and haue bracelets of golde
<pb facs="tcp:174043:35"/> on their armes, neckes, feete, and breaſtes. There be women that liue like harlots, and the <hi>Indians</hi> knowe not what ſinne is. Some women vſe to weare their hayre blacke, which couller among them is much ſet by. In the inner <hi>India</hi> which is that in the middeſt of the three, they conſent not that one man haue more then one woman. In the other they haue as many as they liſt or can get. The manner of their buryals is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in all the <hi>India,</hi> but diuerſe and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one from another. The foremoſt <hi>India</hi> exceedeth the others in ſumptuouſneſſe of their burials: for they make vaultes vnder the grounde, wel and cunningly wrought, &amp; lay the dead body in a bed coſtly decked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> golde and clothes verye precious. In the middlemoſt <hi>India</hi> they burne the bodyes, &amp; the firſte and beſtbeloued wife of him that dyeth, is burned with her huſbande. They weepe and bewayle them that dye dyuerſe kindes of wayes. The <hi>Indians</hi> which are fartheſt within the countrey couer their heads with a ſacke, and ſome put bowes of trees by the wayes, with verſes written, &amp; painted papers. Theſe play vpon Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; feede the poore: others there be that weepe three days for him that is dead,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:174043:35"/> and the kinſfolkes &amp; neighbours goe to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uſe of the deceaſed, and carry meate with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem, in ſuch ſort, that ther is nothing dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead mans houſe in theſe iii. dayes. Such as bury father or mother, carry a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tter leafe in their mouth: and for the ſpace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f a whole yeare neuer change their appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell: neither eate nor drinke but once a day: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>either pare their nayles, nor hayre of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead, nor beard. The women bewaile ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s dye, by ſtriking themſelues vppon their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reaſtes. Some put in certaine veſſels of gold &amp; ſiluer the aſhes of their Princes. The prieſtes which are called <hi>Bachales,</hi> eate of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beaſt, &amp; eſpecialy of the Oxe, ſaying, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is very profitable for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They eat ryce, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earbs, &amp; fruites. They take but one wife who is burned with her huſbande when he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>th. Throughout all <hi>India</hi> are founde one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind of Philoſophers which are caled <hi>Brag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manes,</hi> Aſtronomers &amp; alſo diuines. They liue long: yea, ſo long vntil they come to be 300. yeares of age. They vſe great ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp; imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Throughout all <hi>India</hi> they worſhip idols, &amp; haue churches verye much like to ours, paynted within w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diuers figures. There are in them idols of ſtone, of gold, ſiluer &amp; Iuorie; ſom are 60. foote long.
<pb facs="tcp:174043:36"/> When they enter into their temple, they waſhe them ſelues with cleane water, and lye downe vppon the ground, and holding vp their feete and handes, they praye, and after kiſſe the earth. They inſence their ſacrifices, offer meates to their gods, and after diſtribute them among the poore to be eaten. The <hi>Chambaytas</hi> onely write in paper, all the reſt in leaues of trees: and of them they make bookes very faire to the ſight: they write from aboue downewarde. There are among the <hi>Indians</hi> many and diuers ſortes of languages. They haue a great nomber of ſlaues. The debtor vnable to pay, is driuen to ſerue the creditour. He that is accuſed of any crime, hauing no wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, doth cleare him ſelfe by his othe only. There is no peſtilence in the <hi>Indias,</hi> nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other contagious diſeaſes: and for that cauſe there is a great multitude of people. There are many kings which make an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of more then of one Milleon of men.</p>
            <p>It is ſayed, that in the realme of <hi>Lambry</hi> are men hauing fethers about their ſecrete parts, both great and long like vnto Geeſe. And in <hi>Fanſur</hi> is a kinde of great trees which haue a thin rynde, and vnder it is ful of meale very good, of the which they make
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:174043:36"/> meate very excellent. In all theſe Ilands, becauſe there is want of wine, they make it of certeine trees like to Date trees: of the which they breake the bowes, where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth out certeine white and red licour like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wine, and is very excellent to drinke: and there is great ſtore of it. All thoſe people liue beaſtly, and haue no manner of lawe.</p>
            <p>They worſhip the firſt thing that they ſee in the morning. They eate of all dead fleſh good or euill, and fleſh of mankinde, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing care howe it dye. In the realme of <hi>Biſina</hi> are Munkeis of diuers ſortes, and Vnicornes little leſſer then Elephants, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing heads like to a Pigg, and a long black horne in their forehead, and their tongues ſharpe and thornie with thornes, long and great. The Apes are little and haue their faces like to young children: they flea them, and then ſeeth them, and dreſſe them with ſpices in ſuch ſort, that there remaine no euill ſmell, and ſo eate them. There are in this countrey blacke valiant hawkes like to Crowes, and good for the game. In the ſame countrie, when any dieth, his kinſfolks eate him, &amp; keepe the bones in a cheſt. They kill all the ſtrangers that they take, and forthwith eat them, if they be not redeemed.
<pb facs="tcp:174043:37"/> The people of <hi>Nicuneya</hi> liue like beaſtes and go naked both men and women. They vſe them ſelues like beaſtes in all thinges. In <hi>Nangama</hi> the people are idolaters, they liue beaſtly and eate mans fleſhe; They are very cruell: they haue heads like to great maſtiues, and teeth like to dogges teethe.</p>
            <p>There is in this Ilande great quantitie of ſpices. And departing from this countrey declyning towards the Weſt, one thouſand myles, which are two hundred and fiftie leages, you ſhall come to the Iland called <hi>Saylan</hi> or <hi>Zaylan,</hi> which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayneth in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe three thouſande myles, and is the beſt Iland of the worlde, and the richeſt. The people are Idolaters. They haue aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Ryce and cattell, and wine made as we haue ſayde. There are in it the beſt Rubies of the worlde, and many other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones, as <hi>Topacios, Amatiſtas,</hi> and others of diuerſe ſortes. The king of this Ilande hath a Rubie, the beſt of the world, a ſpanne long, and as great as an arme, and as redd as fire ſhining without any ſoyle or ſpot. The people of this countrie are very lecherous, and nothing worth for the warres. Neere to this Iland toward the Weſt, fourtie myles, which are tenne
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:174043:37"/> leages, there is a great prouince called <hi>Mohobar,</hi> which is called the greater <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia.</hi> This is the greateſt and the beſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince in the worlde: there are in it Pearles very great and fine, and it is deuided into fiue realmes: and all the men and women go naked, ſauing they carry a linnen cloth, wherewith they couer their ſecrete places. Alſo the king goeth naked, ſauing becauſe he will be knowen, he carryeth a ſtring at his necke full of precious ſtones, which are in nomber 54. in remembrance of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny prayers, which he is bound to ſaye, in the honour of their gods, morning and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and vpon his armes, legges, and feet, he carryeth as manye precious ſtones, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enne riche cities are worth. This king hath eyght hundred women. In this realme are faire women, according to there faſhion, they paynt their faces and bodyes. When the king dyeth, they burne him, and all ſuch with him as kept him compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in his life. There is a cuſtome in this lande, that ſuch as are condemned to death, kill themſelues for the loue they beare to their Idols.</p>
            <p>In this countrey euery one hath as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye wyues as he can mayntayne. And
<pb facs="tcp:174043:38"/> when the huſband dyeth, they burne the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy according to their faſhion, and the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of their owne accorde leape into the fire. All thoſe are idolaters, and for the moſt parte worſhip the Oxe, ſaying he is a ſaint, becauſe he ploweth the grounde where the wheat groweth, and therefore will not kill an Oxe for any thing in the worlde, nor eate of his fleſh. And when any Oxe dyeth, they annoynt all the houſe with his tallowe.</p>
            <p>Theſe people deſcend of ſuch as killed ſaint <hi>Thomas.</hi> The king and all the reſt eate their meate vpon the ground. There gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth nothing elſe in this countrey but Rice. All men and women do waſh them ſelues twice a day, morning and euening, and he that faileth therein ſhalbe taken for an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike. They are good in the handeling of their weapons: and fewe of them drinke wine. This countrey is of an intollerable heate, and it neuer rayneth in it, ſauing at certeine times in Iune, Iuly, and Auguſt. There are in this region many Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, Necromancers, and Soothſayers, and blacke hawkes like to crowes, &amp; great Owles like to Hennes. In this prouince the body of Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> the Apoſtle ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth buryed in a ſmall citie. And there liue
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:174043:38"/> many Chriſtians. The men of this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey do annoynt them ſelues with Benia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min to make them the blacker: for the blac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker they are, the fayrer they thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be: and they paynt theyr Idoles blacke, and the diuels white. In all this <hi>India,</hi> they obſerue neyther lawe nor order in their maryages. By this courſe of the ſea towardes the South, are two Ilands of Chriſtians, thirtye myles one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the one of men, the other of women: and the men go not to the women, nor the women to the men, but three monethes in the yeare, Auguſt, September, and Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. The men children remaine with their mothers vntill they be ſeuen yeares of age, and then they go to their fathers. They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue by fleſh, milke, fiſhe, and Ryce, hauing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o other victuals. In this Ilande is great quantitie of Ambar. <hi>Mandagaiſter</hi> is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Ilande towardes the South, diſtant from <hi>Eſcorcia</hi> neare 250. leages. It hath in compaſſe one thouſande &amp; fourtie miles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich are 260. leages. It hath foure kings Mores. There is not eaten in it any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leſhe then of Elefants and Camels, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f there be many: and therefore there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat trafique with Elefants tooth. There
<pb facs="tcp:174043:39"/> are founde in this Ilande certeine birdes that are called <hi>Nichas,</hi> ſo great, that the greateſt Feathers of their Winges are twelue paces long: they are of ſo greate ſtrength, that they take an Elephant, and carrye him vp into the ayre, and kill him, and after let him fall and feede vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him at their pleaſure. <hi>Tanquibar</hi> is another Ilande moſte noble, and lyeth in the ſame courſe, and hath in circuite 250. leages. The inhabiters thereof are Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, and ſo great of ſtature, that they be like Giantes, and are of great force.</p>
            <p>They be all blacke and go naked. They are to be wondered at. The women are foule and euil fauoured. They are ſtrong in battell: for they eſteeme not their liues.</p>
            <p>Returning to the cities of <hi>Cataya</hi> and <hi>Tartaria:</hi> It is ſayde, that the citie of <hi>Berengalia</hi> hath in circuite three ſcore myles, which are fifteene leages, and that it hath nyne hundred thouſande men, that can carrye armour. The men of that countrie take as many wiues as they liſt, who are burned with their huſbands when they dye. And the king hath twelue thouſande, of the which two or three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:174043:39"/> are taken vppon condicion, that when the king dyeth, they of their owne accorde ſhall burne with him, and to theſe is done great honour. In the citie of <hi>Berengalia</hi> three times in the yeare they make a greate feaſt to their goddes: they carrye their Idoles through the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in proceſſion, in the middeſt of two cartes, accompanyed with many people, and manye maydens finely arrayed, ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ioyfully with great deuotion: they ſpende three dayes in bankets, daunces and ſonges: and celebrate their marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages with bankets, ſonges, and trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets. They haue all kinde of Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments as we haue, except Organs, which they lacke. They dawnce as wee do, one after an other, which is a thing to be ſeene. They vſe bathes, except it bee ſuch as are neare to <hi>Ganges.</hi> The other waſhe them ſelues manye tymes a daye in tolde water.</p>
            <p>Neare to this citie of <hi>Berengalia</hi> is a mountayne ſo called, in the which are manye Diamonds, and the mountayne is full of ſerpents, but they take them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye. They which dwell in theſe countreys, deuide the yeare into xii. partes as we do, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:174043:40"/> accompt the moneths like to the xii. ſignes. The moſt part recken the yeare from Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, by <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar.</hi> In ſome of thoſe realmes, they vſe certeine ſmall ſtones for money, which are called the eyes of a Catt. In others they vſe certeine ſmall Irons like to needles: in others, certeine papers wherein is written the name of the king. In ſome prouinces of the <hi>India,</hi> more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, they vſe <hi>Venice</hi> duccats of golde: in others they haue money of ſiluer, and cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: in others they make pieces of golde, and vſe them for money. <hi>Malpuria,</hi> or <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapuria,</hi> or <hi>Milipar</hi> is an other citie in the prouince of <hi>Mahabaria,</hi> neare to the ſecond entrance that the riuer <hi>Indo</hi> doth runne in at, where the body of ſaint <hi>Thomas</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle is honorably buryed in an honorable church, where are reſident well neare 1000 Chriſtians of the <hi>Neſtorians:</hi> of the which are many throughout all the <hi>India,</hi> euen as the Iewes are here among vs. In the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince of <hi>Macino,</hi> which <hi>Volaterano</hi> thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to be the region of the <hi>Seras,</hi> are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Elephants. The king bringeth vp tenne thouſande, and vſeth of them in his warres. The men of this countrey take but one wife apeece. The women are verye lecherous.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:174043:40"/> They are all Idolaters, and in the morning they turne towards the Sunne. They wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the diuinitie of God in Trinitie. In this region is a ryuer called <hi>Daua,</hi> well neare as great as <hi>Ganges:</hi> the citie is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Dua:</hi> it hath 18000. paces in circuite: they write in the leaues of certeine trees, for in all the <hi>India</hi> is no paper, except onely in the citie of <hi>Cambayta.</hi> They eate Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents that are vi. foote in length, &amp; as gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e as a man. They eate likewiſe Ants which are red and as great as crabbes. In the end of this region towards <hi>Cataya,</hi> are certeine Oxen, white, and blacke, with maynes and tayles like horſes, hauing longer hayre.</p>
            <p>The hayres of their tayles are very ſmall, &amp; as light as fethers: they ſell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by waight: they are highly eſteemed. <hi>Cibalechia</hi> is a royall citie, and one of the chiefeſt in all <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taya,</hi> it hath xxviii. miles in circuite: and in the middeſt a pallace very ſtrong and faire: and at euery end a round fort of foure miles compaſſe, for a houſe of armour, where is all kinde of armour, and engins neceſſarye, and that may be imagined for the warres. From the kings pallace to euery one of theſe fortes, is a wall with arches: from whence the king may paſſe to any of them.
<pb facs="tcp:174043:41"/> 
               <hi>Volaterrano</hi> caleth this citie <hi>Cubaleſchia,</hi> and ſayeth it hath 32. thouſand paces in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit: and it ſhoulde ſeeme to bee the ſame <hi>Cambalu</hi> which we haue heretofore ſpoken of. About fifteene dayes iourney from this citie is an other citie called <hi>Neptay</hi> new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buylt, hauing in circuite thirtie myles and very full of people. <hi>Nicholao</hi> did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that the houſes and palaces, and all other things of theſe two cities were verye like to our houſes, and that the men were modeſt, and full of curteſie, and very riche. Neare the citie of <hi>Paconia,</hi> he found vines, yet very fewe: for all the <hi>India,</hi> as is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die declared, lacketh wine, and grapes, and the grapes that there be, growe of trees, and therewith they make ſacrifice to their gods.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Coloen</hi> is a noble Citie, twelue myles in compas: it hath neare to the ſame much Gynger, Pepper, and Cloues. And there be many ſerpentes of diuers kyndes, ſome of ſixe cubites in length wonderfull to be ſeene, but they do no harme. Others haue foure feete and a long tayle like to a dogge: they take them in hunting, and eat them, and report it to be verye good meate. Others there are of the length of a Cubite
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:174043:41"/> with winges that haue ſeuen heads ſet in order by the length of their bodyes, and liue in trees: and flye ſwiftly, and are ſo full of poyſon, that onely with their breath they kill. There are alſo cattes of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes that flye. <hi>Cochin</hi> is an other ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that hath fiue myles in circuite, and ſtandeth at the entrie of a ryuer, of the which it taketh his name: wherein there are ſayde to be fiſhes in a manner like to men and women without any great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. And paſſing farther, they go to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother citie that is called <hi>Colichuchia,</hi> conteyning viii. myles in circuits, which is the moſte famous and noble of trade in all <hi>India.</hi> Here is much Pepper, Lacar, Ginger, and groſe Cinamon, and manye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſweete ſpices. In this region onely the women take as many huſbandes as they liſte: and the huſbandes agree among them ſelues, and euery one contributeth towardes the womans mayntenance, and dwelleth in his owne houſe, and when he goeth to the woman he leaueth a ſigne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the doore. Euery manchilde is the huſbandes, to whome the wife will giue him. Their inheritaunce fall not to the ſonnes, but to the couſines.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:174043:42"/>
            <p>This citie, according to the ſignes &amp; ſhewes is <hi>Calicut.</hi> From hence fifteene days iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, he came to the citie of <hi>Cambayta,</hi> nere to the ſea, whoſe circuite is xii. miles, &amp; is towardes the Weſt, hauing great aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of <hi>Eſpico nardo, Lacat, Indico, Mirabolanos</hi> and <hi>Sarge.</hi> There is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine kinde of Prieſtes that are called <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chales,</hi> which haue but one wife, who bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth her ſelfe with her huſband when he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Theſe eate of no kinde of beaſt, but liue with fruites of the Earth, Rice, milk, and wild hearbes. In this citie the prieſtes do preache to the people in the preſence of their Idols. And many kill themſelues for the honour of their gods: and thoſe that ſo do, are taken among them for Saintes.</p>
            <p>There are many Oxen of the mountaynes, that haue maynes lyke horſes, and hornes ſo long, that if they turne their heads, they reche with them their tayles. Neare to this citie lyeth two Ilandes diſtant a hundreth miles a ſunder: the one inhabited with wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and the other with men: one while the men paſſe to the women, another while the women to the men, euery one returning within ſixe moneths to their owne Ilands: for they thinke, if they continued any longer
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:174043:42"/> together, that they ſhould dye: of the which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eople we haue before ſpoken. There re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth behinde, for the concluſion of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eregrination, to treat of a region of the <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as,</hi> who by the North parte do border vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Seras</hi> towardes the Weſt: but it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nowen what countries there are on the South parte, but that it is wilderneſſe. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Weſt, the <hi>India</hi> lyeth neare to <hi>Ganges</hi> vnto the great gulfe that is called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he South ſea: where it is ſayde, that the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cthiafagi,</hi> to wit, ſuch as liue onely with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſh, dwel. It hath many cities. The metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olitan and principall of all, is the citie of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ina,</hi> which is at the South parte. Of this <hi>Ptolomeo</hi> ſpeaketh, reporting it to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er the Equinoctiall line: and that it exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth vnto the <hi>Antecos,</hi> which are on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her ſide of the South. The countrey of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igara</hi> encloſeth it on the Weſt parte, &amp; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nknowen countrie, vnto the <hi>Promontorio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raſo,</hi> and the ſea of <hi>Praſodia. Gatigara</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>port and a principall place, where the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hips do ryde and harbour in this region. And <hi>Aſpithra</hi> is a riuer, and great citie in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſame. <hi>Calicut, Canonor, Cambayta, Narſinga,</hi> are no newe regions: for in truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey were knowen of the auncient writers,
<pb facs="tcp:174043:43"/> and in our time haue beene diſcouered, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and wonderfull things which are found in theſe Eaſt <hi>Indias</hi> newely diſcouered by the Spanyardes, but eſpecially in euery region of the ſame are ſome precious thinges more in particular, as in the kingdome of <hi>Calicute</hi> and <hi>Narſinga</hi> gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth Pepper, Ginger, <hi>Cardamo, Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolanos</hi> and <hi>Caſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Cambaya</hi> and <hi>Cochin</hi> is much <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piquenardo</hi> and <hi>Mirabolannos</hi> and alſo cotten wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l in aboundance. In the realme of <hi>Pego</hi> are al the like. And likewiſe the ſtone <hi>Cornerina,</hi> the <hi>Calcedonia</hi> &amp; the diamo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds. In the Iland of <hi>Armos</hi> are ſtones in great aboundance. In the Iland of <hi>Zailon</hi> which is <hi>Taprobana</hi> are found Rubies and Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinets, Saphires and Topacios. In the realme of <hi>Melaca</hi> are many Popingeys, and E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ephants. In <hi>Sumotra</hi> is great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundaunce of Pepper. The <hi>Camfora</hi> is found in the Iland of <hi>Porne,</hi> in <hi>Monoch</hi> &amp; <hi>Bandan</hi> which are Ilands. Neare to theſe partes, are Nutmegs, and Cloues great ſtore, The Iland of <hi>Sipangry</hi> hath much golde and great riches. The Iland of <hi>Petar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and both <hi>Iauas</hi> yeld great ſtore of Pepper,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:174043:43"/> Nutmegs, Eſpique, of <hi>Galanga</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſwete odours. In <hi>Madagaſſar</hi> are many Elefants, and great aboundance of Iuory very fyne.</p>
            <p>The Ilande of <hi>Zauzibar</hi> is verye much like to this, abounding with Lyons, and many other wilde beaſtes. <hi>Nicolao Veneciano,</hi> as <hi>Pogio</hi> declareth, reporteth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the ſmall brooks of the ryuer <hi>Ganges</hi> there were canes of a meruailous length, &amp; ſo great that a man could ſkarcely inſorace them about with both armes, with the which they made ſmall Boates to ſaile in, and at euery ſyde of thoſe brookes are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny gardeynes and orchardes very pleaſant and full of delyght. And there groweth a fruite verye like to Figges that they call <hi>Muſa,</hi> which is exceeding ſweete, yea, ſweeter then honye. It is ſayde, that the Ilande <hi>Taprobana</hi> conteyneth ſixteene thouſande tymes, a hundreth thouſand pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in circuite, which amount to foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred leages, accompting foure Engliſhe myles to euery leag. The men of that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande were verye cruell in their manners, and both the men and women haue verye great eares, laden with <hi>Zarcillos</hi> of gold, &amp; precious ſtones: and they weare linnen
<pb facs="tcp:174043:44"/> loth, and cloth of <hi>Sarge.</hi> And the men take many wiues, and haue lowe houſes, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the great heat, and are Idolaters, and haue great ſtore of Pepper, of that ſorte which is called the greateſt, &amp; of the toung, and plentie of Canfora, and Golde. In a certeine place of this Ilande, which they call <hi>Bateth</hi> are a kind of people called <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropophagi,</hi> to wit, deuowrers of men, in reſpect that they eat the fleſhe of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and keepe their heades for treaſure: and he that hath moſt heads, is accounted moſt riche: for they make a trade with them and barter them away for other things. In <hi>Armenia</hi> the great, there is reported to be a fountayne, where water like oyle ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, in ſo great abundance, that many ſhippes are laden therewith. It is good to burne for light, and to annoynt beaſtes. In the land of <hi>Tartaria</hi> towards the North, are doggs not much leſſe then Aſſes, the which drawe a frame of timber, like as if it were a Cart, ſauing that it goeth not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wheeles, vpon the which two men may go, and they put two or foure dogges or more to it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the burthen and neceſſitie. At the ende of this realme, is a countrie called <hi>Darkneſſe:</hi> becauſe it is alwayes as darke
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:174043:44"/> as the firſt houre of the night: &amp; the Sunne is neuer ſeene there. In this countrey are handſome men and women of perſon, but yellowe in couler. They haue neither king nor lawe, but liue like beaſtes. This coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey ioyneth with one parte of <hi>Ruſsia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ruſsia</hi> is a great prouince towardes the North, &amp; a ſtrong countrey. There are in it faire men and women, and are Chriſtians. They pay tribute to the king of <hi>Tartaria.</hi> There is great ſtore of coſtly ſkinnes and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rres. There are in <hi>Ruſsia</hi> many mynes of ſiluer: the countrie is very colde. In the ſame time <hi>Pogio</hi> declareth that there came certeine men from <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> which is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of the <hi>Indias</hi> and the countrey of <hi>Preſter Iohn,</hi> and declared that they were of the countrey, nere whereunto the riuer <hi>Nile</hi> ſpringeth: and alſo ſayd that the ſame riuer ſpringeth neare to the Equinoctiall at the foote of certeine high mountaynes, that are alwayes couered with clowdes: and that the ſayd riuer groweth of three great foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines: two of them which are 40. paces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder, &amp; theſe meete together at the ende of 500. paces, &amp; then make the riuer ſo great, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it cannot be waded through. The thirde fountayne is a greater ſtreame, &amp; a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande
<pb facs="tcp:174043:45"/> paces from the other, and is neare to his riuer, and tenne myles from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ryuers. They ſaye that there runne aboue a thouſande riuers into the riuer of <hi>Nile.</hi> And in the monethes of Marche, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril, and Maye, the rayne ſo much increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in that countrey, that they cauſe the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers to ouerflowe, and great floods to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe thereof. They ſaye alſo that the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Nile</hi> is verye ſweete, before it min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleth with other ryuers, and that it had vertue to heale the leproſie and ſcabbes, of ſuch as waſhed them ſelues therein: Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that very neere about the place where the riuer <hi>Nile</hi> ſpringeth, there ſtandeth a citie where they were borne that had 25. myles in circuite, which is vi. leagues &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, and that it was inhabited with peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And they ſayde, that this region neare to <hi>Nile</hi> was verye temperate and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant of all thinges. In ſo much tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thrice a yeare they had Haye growing and mowen: and twyce Wheate, and had abundaunce of breade and wyne, and of all fruites like to ours, but Almondes ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> want. And the moſte parte of <hi>Aethiopia</hi> in ſteede of Wine vſe Water tempere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with Barley. They ſayd that vnto the Ilan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:174043:45"/> of <hi>Meroe,</hi> the riuer of <hi>Nile</hi> was not naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able by reaſon of the great no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of rocks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat are in it: and that from the ſame I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ande forwarde, ſhippes might eaſilye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayle and paſſe. Men being aſked of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> which is of the <hi>Indias</hi> of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Iohn,</hi> vppon the ſayde ryuer, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe that here wee ſpeake of, reported <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat thoſe people of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>only of a longer lyfe then wee are of, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd many of them liue a hundred and fiftie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ares, and in ſome places two hundred<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey neuer haue the Peſtilence nor other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>firmities: and that therefore it is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e populous countrey. They haue no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oll: they apparell them ſelues with lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n cloth, or with ſilke both men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en, and the women for the moſte parte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rrye behinde them a long trayne, and goe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rte with certeine broade gyrdels garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with golde, and precious ſtones <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome couer their heads with thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at are wouen in with Golde, others carry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir haire looſe. Both men and women v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>weare rings on their fingers, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>all tables to eat vppon: they couer th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>we do. All thoſe people haue one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ters, but diuerſe languages.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:174043:46"/>
            <p>They haue one king, who is intituled king of kings vnder God. There are in <hi>Aethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> Oxen, that are crooked backt like Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels with hornes of three foote long. Their dogges be as great as our Aſſes. They can do more then Lyons, and they hunt Lyons with them. There are many Elefants that haue teeth of ſixe foote in length. There are diuers other beaſts, which differ from ours, and alſo birdes. They ſayde, that in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts were ſerpents of 50. foote of length without feete, that would ſwallowe vp a whole calfe. Vpon the riuer <hi>Eufrates</hi> is a noble citie, whoſe circuite is of 14. thouſand paces. They ſaye, that it is one parte of the auncient <hi>Babylon:</hi> It is called <hi>Baldach,</hi> or <hi>Baldachia:</hi> &amp; <hi>Eufrates</hi> paſſeth through the middeſt thereof. It hath one gate of 14. arches. There appeare from theſe parts many tokens of that great and auncient <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London, at the three Cranes in the Vintree, <hi>by Thomas Dawſon.</hi> 1580.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
